## YASSER GONZALEZ

Curriculum Vitae – October 2015

**Website** – http://yassergonzalez.com **Email** – contact@yassergonzalez.com **Phone** – 1-647-767-0942

### **SUMMARY**

With a background in computer science and experience as research assistant, I'm passionate about the design and implementation of algorithms to solve challenging problems and draw conclusions from data. I have a keen interest in data science – including the areas of optimization, machine learning, and natural language processing. I love working with open-source technologies, started 10 years ago and haven't stopped since then.

# **EDUCATION**

2013-2015

Master's degree, Information Systems & Technology.

York University, Canada.

- Thesis: Efficient Calculation of Optimal Configuration Processes.
- Relevant Courses: Mining of Massive Datasets, Advanced Information Retrieval Systems, Introduction to Computational Linguistics.

### 2014-2015

Data Science Specialization.

A non-credit series offered by Johns Hopkins University through Coursera.

• Relevant Courses: R Programming, Getting and Cleaning Data, Exploratory Data Analysis, Statistical Inference, Regression Models.

#### 2006-2011

Bachelor's degree, Computer Science.

University of Havana, Cuba.

- *GPA*: 5.0/5.0 (Summa Cum Laude).
- Thesis: Estimation of Distribution Algorithms Based on Copulas and Vines.
- Relevant Courses: Linear Algebra, Calculus, Probability & Statistics,
  Design & Analysis of Algorithms, Operating Systems, Computer Networks,
  Database Systems, Artificial Intelligence, Information Retrieval Systems.

## **TECHNOLOGIES**

Python – R – C – Java – HTML – CSS – JavaScript SQL – Hadoop – Git – GNU/Linux system administration.

## **EXPERIENCE**

2013-2015

Research & Teaching Assistant. York University, Canada.

- Designed different solution methods for the problem of optimizing the user interaction in a configuration process.
- Developed techniques to improve the performance of search heuristics on multimodal optimization problems.
- Programmed scientific software in Python (using NumPy, pandas, and SciPy), R, and MATLAB/Octave.

## 2011-2013

**Research Assistant**. Institute of Cybernetics, Mathematics and Physics, Cuba.

- Created new estimation of distribution algorithms (EDAs) using copulas and vines to model the probability distributions.
- Implemented a group of R packages available on CRAN, and a C library for dependence modeling using vines.
- Co-supervised a bachelor's thesis in computer science.

#### SELECTED OPEN-SOURCE SOFTWARE

- **configurator** Python package providing different solutions to the problem of optimizing the user interaction in a configuration process. https://github.com/yasserglez/configurator.
- **copulaedas** R package for implementing and studying estimation of distribution algorithms (EDAs) based on copulas. https://github.com/yasserglez/copulaedas.
- **vines** R implementation of the vine graphical model for building high-dimensional probability distributions as a factorization of bivariate copulas and marginal density functions. https://github.com/yasserglez/vines.
- **ngram\_profile** Python library for text classification based on character n-grams. https://github.com/yasserglez/ngram\_profile.
- **dml** C library for dependence modeling using C-vines, D-vines and R-vines. https://github.com/yasserglez/dml.

For more information, please see http://yassergonzalez.com/software.

### **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

- Y. Gonzalez-Fernandez, S. Chen. (2015). Leaders and Followers A New Metaheuristic to Avoid the Bias of Accumulated Information. In *IEEE Congress* on *Evolutionary Computation*, 776–783. IEEE. http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/CEC.2015.7256970.
- Y. Gonzalez-Fernandez, M. Soto. (2014). copulaedas: An R Package for Estimation of Distribution Algorithms Based on Copulas. *Journal of Statistical* Software, 58(9), 1–34. http://www.jstatsoft.org/v58/i09.
- Y. Gonzalez-Fernandez, S. Chen. (2014). Identifying and Exploiting the Scale of a Search Space in Particle Swarm Optimization. In *Conference on Genetic and Evolutionary Computation*, 17–24. ACM. http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/2576768.2598280.
- Y. Gonzalez-Fernandez, D. Carrera, M. Soto, A. Ochoa. (2012). Vine Estimation of Distribution Algorithms. In VIII Congreso Español sobre Metaheurísticas, Algoritmos Evolutivos y Bioinspirados, 1–7. http://simd.albacete.org/maeb2012/papers/paper\_99.pdf.

For more information, please see http://yassergonzalez.com/publications.